[Music]
is cannabis impaired driving a public
health and safety concern well the
number of tickets went up for cannabis
impaired driving in Washington state
after legalization and the proportion of
drivers and fatal car crashes in
Colorado who tested positive went up but
in both cases this may simply reflect
the general increase in marijuana use
overall it doesn't mean that cannabis is
causing the
crashes yeah there's lots of evidence
correlating marijuana use with car
accidents but you have to ask yourself
who uses marijuana mostly young people
and males and guess who has higher crash
risk regardless of what they smoke young
people and
males but taking that into account it
does seem that roughly 20 to 30% of
traffic crashes involving cannabis use
occur because of the cannabis use
uh to put that in perspective though
that number is more like
85% when it comes to
alcohol yeah but are the Cannabis
crashes just like low velocity fender
bender bumps from some wasted driver
going like 5 mil hour after a systematic
review of the literature this
compilation of studies examining acute
cannabis consumption and motor vehicle
collisions found a near doubling of risk
of a driver being involved in a motor
vehicle collision resulting in serious
injury or death so that's pretty serious
though again alcohol is even worse yes
cannabis May double or triple the risk
of car crashes but alcohol may multiply
the risk like 6 to 15 full uh the combo
may be even worse though 25 times the
odds of fatal car crash involvement
testing positive for both the safety
consequence of cannabis intoxication
when driving is listed as a primary
concern about cannabis
legalization okay well what happened in
the states where marijuana was legalized
how much did traffic fatalities go up
they didn't in fact they went down what
why does legalizing pot reduce traffic
fatalities because it reduced alcohol
consumption they found that legalization
of weed was associated with reduced
alcohol consumption so yes more drugged
driving but less drunk driving and
that's so much worse that overall
fatalities went
down so perhaps we'd also see less liver
disease less alcohol induced brain
damage as pot substitutes for some of
the alcohol use cannabis is unlikely to
produce as much harm as alcohol because
unlike alcohol cannabis does not cause
liver or gastrointestinal diseases not
fatal in overdoses and does not appear
as neurotoxic as alcohol and it's not as
potent a cause of car crashes as alcohol
either the health problems of cannabis
dependence like bronchitis and memory
impairment are much less serious on
average than those suffering from
alcohol dependence but this does not
mean that cannabis dependence is a minor
problem but you know Public Health
authorities can be criticized for
bringing that up it's like in the 40s
and 50s after the repeal of prohibition
you still need to warn people about the
problems of heavy drinking and liver
therosis alcoholism but you just get
dismissed as some Temperance
propagandist and now we see a similar
thing where the public health profession
wants to educate people about the
adverse health effects of cannabis but
are dismissed as reer Madness
hysterics still it's important to put
these adverse health effects in
perspective how does the safety of
cannabis Stack Up against alcohol and
tobacco well according to the CDC
alcohol is linked to approximately
88,000 deaths per year whereas the death
due to cannabis are from things like car
accidents and they go down when more
people smoke pot because alcohol is so
much
worse with hindsight we can clearly see
the enormous problems that have been
caused by the legal drugs tobacco and
alcohol if asked to decide today which
site oactive drugs should be legal
cannabis might well be much higher on
the
[Music]
list